Alan Dunn and Mary Petty Papers
Alan Dunn and Mary Petty Papers
1907-1972
Dunn, Alan, 1900-
21 linear ft.
The papers of the American cartoonists for The New Yorker (1926-1974) include correspondence (letters from John Taylor Arms, Peggy Bacon, Isabel Bishop, Warren Chappell, Eric Hodgins, and Alan Watts); cartoons and drawings; exhibition catalogs; notebooks; business files and financial records; and memorabilia, including clippings, photographs, and scrapbooks..
149628
Biographical History
Alan Dunn (1900-1974) and his wife Mary Petty (1899-1976) were American cartoonists. They married in 1927, and for more than thirty years lived in a modest, three-bedroom apartment in Manhattan that also served as their studio. They rarely left the city and, although they were members of several professional organizations and clubs and attended social events, Mary Petty and Alan Dunn spent a great deal of time developing their art and a unique view of life.
Alan Dunn studied at Columbia University, the National Academy of Design and the American Academy in Rome, an experience which provided him with a particular insight about both European cultures and American tourists. When he returned to the United States, his mild satire was well-received by magazines such as the newly established New Yorker, who began publishing his cartoons in 1926. Thanks to Dunn’s expertise at drawing architecture (beginning in 1936 he contributed regularly to "Architectural Record") viewers can easily identify European settings in his cartoons such as the Roman Forum and the Basilica of Maxentius, and his social satires often illustrate American tourists’ provincial nature and myopic sense of superiority. He defined himself as a "social cartoonist, whose pen is no sword but a titillating feather that reminds us that we do not act as we speak or think."
Dunn eventually became the New Yorker's most prolific illustrator, creating 9 covers and nearly 2000 cartoons over 47 years. Several collections of his cartoons were published including Who's Paying for this Cab? (Simon & Schuster, 1945), A Portfolio of Social Cartoons (Simon & Schuster, 1968) and Architecture Observed (New York, 1970). His work has been exhibited at the Art Institute of Chicago, the National Academy of Design, and Salons of America, and he was a member of the American Watercolor Society, the New York Watercolor Society, and Salons of America. According to a paper by Eric M. Jones of the Los Alamos National Laboratory, it was a 1950 cartoon of Dunn's featuring flying saucers stealing trash bins in Manhattan that led noted physicist Enrico Fermi to pose the question "Where is everybody?" This question later became known as the Fermi Paradox and, in conjunction with Drake's Equation, provides the mathematical starting point for much current debate on the possibility of extraterrestrials visiting earth.
Mary Petty graduated from the Horace Mann School in New York City in 1922, and five years later she and Dunn were married. Although Petty underwent no formal art training, she had the firm support of her husband who encouraged her originality and natural talent for drawing and provided artistic guidance. Soon she too was being published in The New Yorker, and over the next four decades created a singular style of illustration characterized by a gentle satirization of New York City's Victorian era society. In a series of 35 covers produced over 26 years, Mary Petty created and chronicled the lives of the Peabody family, including Mrs. Peabody, dowager of the family, and Fay, the whimsical, fragile maid who cared for the aging mistress and her family. These cover illustrations so successfully portrayed the personality quirks of New York's upper class that people would write to remark that they knew a family that must have been the model for these paintings.
Petty published over 200 cartoons in The New Yorker and painted more than 30 watercolors for the front cover of the magazine. Her work was exhibited nationally and internationally during her lifetime. Examples of her art are in the permanent collections of the Museum of Modern Art in New York, the Museum of the City of New York and the Wichita Art Museum in Wichita, Kansas. The largest single collection of her work is owned by the Syracuse University Art Collections, a gift from the artist.
Mary Petty and Alan Dunn believed that gentle, pictorial satire could be as effective as political or editorial comment. Between them they created thousands of drawings that commented upon issues that are still important to us today, reminding us that a genteel manner of examining our culture can still be effective.
[Portions of this biographical sketch adapted from text for "Mary Petty Exhibit" at Syracuse University's Lubin House and from "American Satire: Humor in The New Yorker" at Syracuse University in Florence]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
This collection is partially processed only and remains in original order. Biographical material contains miscellaneous biographical material including a family history. Correspondence, most of which is incoming, includes letters from artists (Peggy Bacon, John Taylor Arms, Isabel Bishop, Felicia Marsh), museums (Cincinnati Art Museum, Cleveland Museum of Art, New York Metropolitan Museum, Museum of Modern Art), publications (Architural Record, Living Screen, Saturday Evening Post), publishers (Alfred Knopf, Bobbs Merrill, Doubleday, Simon & Schuster), and writers (Warren Chappell, Eric Hodgins, Alan Watts). Miscellaneous notes contains poems, cartoons, captions, exhibit catalogs, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, notebooks of ideas. Subject files comprise material on a variety of topics including alcoholism, architecture, human body, investing, New Yorker covers, war, and others.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection is partially processed only and remains in its original order as received.
Related Material
has collections of more than eighty cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Arms, John Taylor, 1887-1953.; Bacon, Peggy, 1895-1987.; Bishop, Isabel, 1902-1988.; Chappell, Warren, 1904-; Dunn, Alan, 1900- Archives.; Hodgins, Eric, 1899-1971.; Petty, Mary Archives.; Watts, Alan, 1915-1973.; New Yorker (New York, N.Y.: 1925); American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons, United States.; Cartoonists, United States.; Women cartoonists.; Cartoons (humorous images); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Exhibition catalogs.; Notebooks.; Scrapbooks.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Family history (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Dunn to Petty, 1926-1927 (Box 1)
  - Petty to Dunn, 1922-48; 1950,; 1953-1971,; undated; 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Dunn, Sarah Benton (Box 1)
  - Dunn, Alan, 1915-1916; 1918-1920; 9 folders (Box 2)
  - Dunn, Alan, 1921-1932; 9 folders (Box 3)
  - 1933-1944, 12 folders (Box 4)
  - 1945-1950, 1954-1961, 12 folders (Box 5)
  - 1962-1971, 10 folders (Box 6)
  - 1972-1974, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - undated (Box 7)
  - New Yorker, 1920's -; 1970's; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Bishop, Isabel (Box 7)
  - Bacon, Peggy & Petty, 1950-1972 (Box 7)
  - Arms, John Taylor (Box 7)
  - Hodgins, Eric (Box 7)
  - Chappell, Warren, 1957; 1968,; 1970-1971 (Box 7)
  - Cincinnati Art Museum (Box 7)
  - Cleveland Museum of Art (Box 7)
  - Darrow, W. (Box 7)
  - Day, Bob (Box 7)
  - Dai News, 1945-1961 (Box 7)
  - deYoung Memorial Museum, San Francisco (Box 7)
  - Dunn, William, 1907 (Box 7)
  - Fortune, 1951-1958 (Box 7)
  - Galleries, general (Box 7)
  - Harper, B., 1941-1963 (Box 7)
  - Harvard University, Fogg. Museum (Box 7)
  - A. Knopf, 11/27/31; 12/17/31 (Box 8)
  - Lathrop, Stanley (Tiffany Foundation) (Box 8)
  - Architural Record, 1930-1950 (Box 8)
  - Mumford, Lewis (Box 8)
  - Living Screen (Box 8)
  - Marsh, Felicia, 1954 (Box 8)
  - New York Metropolitan Museum (Box 8)
  - New York Museum of Modern Art (Box 8)
  - Munson Williams Proctor, Utica (Box 8)
  - Museum of the City of New York (Box 8)
  - Pierson, Hunter, 1952-1971; 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Price, Gerret (Box 8)
  - Publishers
    - Misc. (A-B) (Box 9)
    - Better Homes & Gardens, Book Digest, Bantam (Box 9)
    - Bobbs Merrill, Brandt (Box 9)
    - C-D (Box 9)
    - Doubleday, Dodge (Box 9)
    - E-W (Box 9)
  - Robsjohn-Gibbings (Box 9)
  - Ramsey Advertising Agency, 1961-1972 (Box 9)
  - Rhode Island Museum of Art (Box 9)
  - Saturday Evening Post, 1932-1945 (Box 9)
  - Simon & Schuster, 1934-1960's; 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Slater Memorial Museum, Norwich, Conn (Box 9)
  - Toledo Museum of Art (Box 9)
  - Walton, Bill and Emily Ann Cramer (Box 9)
  - Watts, Alan, 1957-58; 1962-1963,; 1965-1967,; 72 (Box 9)
  - Watts, Alan, Printed material (Box 9)
  - White, Nelson, 1920-24; 1928-1931,; 1933-1936,; 1938,; 1941-1959; 4 folders (Box 10)
  - Wortman (Box 10)
  - Petty, Mary, 1909-1952; 5 folders (Box 10)
  - Outgoing drafts, ca. 1950-1964; 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Petty, Mary
    - Son and mother cartoon (public responses), 1952 (Box 11)
    - General, 1953-1970; 8 folders (Box 11)
    - General, undated (Box 12)
    - Knopf (Box 12)
    - Maynard Walker Gallery (Box 12)
  - Unidentified (Box 12)
  - Greeting cards (Box 12)
  - Christmas cards, 7 folders (Box 12, 13)
  - Postcards, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Empty envelopes (Box 13)
  - Apartment leases (Box 13)
  - Bank books (Box 13)
  - Bank statements, bills, receipts, etc., 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Income tax information (Box 14)
  - Insurance policies, cancelled checks/stubs (Box 14)
  - Misc. bills & receipts (Box 14)
  - Report cards, membership cards, passport (Box 14)
  - Stocks & transaction information (Box 14)
  - Works, lists of works (Box 14)
  - New Yorker contracts (Box 14)
  - Business records - contracts - Simon & Schuster (Box 14)
  - Simon & Schuster - business records - "East of Fifth" (Box 14)
  - Simon & Schuster - business records - royalty statements - "Is there intelligent life on earth?" (Box 14)
  - Simon & Schuster - business records - "Portfolio of Social Cartoons" (Box 14)
  - Simon & Schuster - business records - "Should it Gurgle?" (Box 14)
  - Simon & Schuster - business records - "Who's paying for this cab?" (Box 14)
  - Business records - vouchers - Arch. R., New York, Simon & Schuster, misc. (Box 14)
  - U. S. Government (Box 14)
  - Fraternity & Cosmopolitan Club (Box 15)
  - Edmund Jacobson relaxation cards (Box 15)
  - Alan Dunn & Mary Petty photographs (Box 15)
  - Stationary samples & misc. memorabilia (Box 15)
  - War Ration book pages (Box 15)
  - Alan Dunn - misc. - printed material (Box 15)
  - Alan Dunn - clippings, notices, articles (Box 15)
  - Alan Dunn - assorted leaflets, brochures (Box 15)
  - WW II military inventions (Box 16)
  - Notes (index cards)
    - Science (Box 16)
    - Edmund Jacobson (Box 16)
    - Otto Rank (Box 16)
    - Science of Life (Box 16)
    - Wine (Box 16)
    - Krishnamurti (Box 16)
    - Alan Watts, Zen, etc. (Box 16)
    - H.C. Wolff (Box 16)
    - Expressions (Box 16)
    - Misc. (Box 16)
- Miscellaneous
  - Notes, 22 folders (Box 17)
  - Mary Petty - poems (by year & month) - price list (Box 18)
  - Alan Dunn - cartoon & caption ideas/Arc. Rec. ideas - notebook pp. (Box 18)
  - Alan Dunn - cartoon reprod's - discards from Rec. - Brussels Exibit (Box 18)
  - Alan Dunn - exhibition catalogs (Box 18)
  - Alan Dunn - gallery invitations (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous catalogs (Box 18)
  - Christmas cards w/Alan Dunn cartoons (Box 18)
  - Alan Dunn - editorial notes - New York, 1943-1960; 1964,; 1967,; undated; 4 folders (Box 18)
  - New York cartoons, 1927-1931; 1944,; 1946,; 1951-1952,; 1955-1956; 5 folders (Box 19)
  - Architectural record (Box 19)
  - Book ads (Box 19)
  - Private purkey (Box 19)
  - "Is there intelligent life on earth?" (Box 19)
  - Rackety rac (Box 19)
  - Exhibitions (Box 19)
  - Newspaper & periodical clippings - Alan Dunn cartoons, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Cartoons by other artists (Box 19)
  - Newsclips (Box 19)
  - Printed Dunn cartoons (Box 19)
  - Poster on cartooning (Box 19)
  - Hizzonor the Mayor (Box 20)
  - Alan Dunn newspaper clippings, miscellaneous (Box 20)
  - Punch In Suzie (Box 20)
  - 6th New York album (Box 20)
  - Dunn Family (Box 20)
  - Rejections (Box 20)
  - Alan Dunn newspaper clippings - "Architecture Observed" (Box 20)
  - Alan Dunn newspaper clippings - "Should It Gurgle" (Box 20)
  - Alan Dunn newspaper clippings - "Who's Paying for this Cab?" (Box 20)
  - Alan Dunn newspaper clippings - "The Last Lath" (Box 20)
  - Alan Dunn newspaper clippings - "East of Fifth" (Box 20)
  - Petty clippings (Box 20)
  - Alan Dunn early sketchbook (original at SUAC) (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 20)
  - Memorabilia related to scouting (Box 20)
  - Scrapbook, 1931 (Box 20)
  - Scrapbook, mixed subjects, 1935 (Box 20)
  - Scrapbook, faces men/women/children (Box 20)
  - Loose Dunn clips (Box 20)
  - Notebooks - mixed study, list of words, 2 items (Box 21)
  - Scrapbook of book reviews - Dunn (Box 21)
  - Captions (used?), Jan 1938 - Sept. 1959; 7 volumes (Box 21)
  - Notebook of subjects & dates (Box 22)
  - Topics (or Topix) (Box 22)
  - Notebooks
    - [untitled], 1938-1956; 9 volumes (Box 22)
    - Architectural Record captions, 2 volumes (Box 22)
    - Names (Box 22)
    - Captions - drugstores, 1948 (Box 22)
    - "Spots" - captions, undated (Box 22)
    - Notebooks & loose notes
      - "Stage War", undated (Box 23)
      - "The War Situational", 1951 (Box 23)
      - "First 3 War Bonds", 1942 (Box 23)
    - Cliches - collected expressions from cliche book, 4 volumes (Box 23)
    - "Nibbles", undated (Box 23)
    - Resubmissions/resubmissables, 2 volumes (Box 23)
    - Gag larder" (Box 23)
    - "Brownstone Book" (Box 23)
    - "Bons du passe" (Box 23)
    - "This Island" - book notes, undated (Box 23)
    - "Sociological Submissions" (Box 23)
    - SRL Possibilities", 1959 (Box 23)
    - "World City - New York" (Box 23)
  - Ideas - World & U.S. Politics, early 1960's (Box 24)
  - Captions, 1962-1967; undated; 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Captions - Contemp May 42 (Box 24)
  - Captions - Ideas & Expressions (not used) (Box 24)
  - Captions - "Firsts", 5 notebooks (Box 24)
  - Captions - From Roughs, 3 notebooks (Box 24)
  - Originalia (Box 24)
  - Caption phraseology (Box 24)
  - Caption reworks (Box 24)
  - Captions - story, 4 notebooks (Box 25)
  - Captions - expression, 5 notebooks (Box 25)
  - Captions - current book, Jan 1, 1947 (Box 25)
  - Captions, April 1951 - June 1953; 2 notebooks (Box 25)
  - Captions, 1953? (Box 25)
  - Ideas, 5 notebooks (Box 25)
  - Ideas - captions, undated; 9 folders (Box 26)
  - Ideas - captions, undated; 4 folders (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous - pictorial classification (Box 27)
  - Essay drafts (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous captions/titles/ideas (Box 27)
  - "Collegiatism - A Disease" (Box 27)
  - "The Daily Event" v.1, Nov. 28, 1912 (Box 27)
  - "Disillusionment of a young painter" (Box 27)
  - "Don't Tell Everything" (Box 27)
  - "Ek and Ulg: The Real Adam & Eve" (Box 27)
  - "Enough Time, The Pattern of the Executive Life" by Eric Hodgins, See also Package 1 (Box 27)
  - "Environment", poem fragment (Box 27)
  - "An Essay on Civility" (Box 27)
  - "Eternal City" (Box 27)
  - "Every Moment..." - untitled quote (Box 27)
  - "The Finest Man in the World" - by D. C. Allen, See also "Don't tell everything". (Box 27)
  - "Focus of Attention - a Study" (Box 27)
  - "Gilding the Dandelion" (Box 27)
  - "Goodbye Manhattan" first draft (Box 27)
  - "Goodbye Manhattan" last draft (Box 27)
  - "Graphic Comment Art" (Box 27)
  - "I Became a Stray Cat" (Box 27)
  - "I Remember, a Pictorial Autobiography of an artist's childhood - an adventure in beauty" (Box 27)
  - "Individuality" (Box 27)
  - "Ingio Schulane" movie scenario (Box 27)
  - "Ingio Schulane" story (Box 27)
  - "Is there Intelligent Life On Earth?" working draft (Box 28)
  - "Is there Intelligent Life On Earth?" - A Report to the Congress of Mars, incoplete draft (Box 28)
  - "Is there Intelligent Life On Earth?" - A Report to the Congress of Mars, typescript carbon (Box 28)
  - "Is there Intelligent Life On Earth?", miscellaneous (Box 28)
  - "Is there Intelligent Life On Earth?" screenplay (Box 28)
  - "Just As The Little Fishes" (Box 28)
  - "Lapis Blue", first draft; final drafts; 3 folders (Box 28)
  - "Lapis Blue", manuscript pages, drawing (Box 28)
  - "Lapis Blue", copy manuscripts (Box 28)
  - "Lapis Blue", original drawings and manuscript (Box 29)
  - Poem, "Long gloomy..." (Box 29)
  - "The Man is insane" (Box 29)
  - Metabolism, resume on (Box 29)
  - "Museum bars" (Box 29)
  - Nazi guide to America (Box 29)
  - "New Theory of Temperament" (Box 29)
  - "Pulsar One - A Fantasy for the Knowledgeable Child" (Box 29)
  - "Rabbit" (Box 29)
  - "Rabbit" by Alan North (Box 29)
  - "Recent Rejection Slips" revised by Alan Dunn (Box 29)
  - "Rum Runner's Romance" (Box 29)
  - "S P Therapy" (Box 29)
  - "Sensation of Beauty" (Box 29)
  - "Should it Gurgle" (Box 29)
  - "Should it Gurgle", working title: If it weren't for Russia (Box 29)
  - "Six Billion People", illustrations (Box 30)
  - "Six Billion People", incomplete drafts; 6 folders (Box 30)
  - "Six Billion People", manuscript (Box 30)
  - "The Somers Portrait of Helen" by George Gaignes, See also "They're brothers under the skin". (Box 30)
  - "Taste", 3d draft (Box 30)
  - "They're Brothers Under the Skin" - by George Gaignes, See also "The Somers portrait...". (Box 30)
  - "You Can't Go Home Again" (Box 30)
  - "Your Day of Rest" (Box 30)
  - Writings for - "Talk of the Town" (Box 31)
  - School notes? (Box 31)
  - Book notes, 4 folders (Box 31)
  - Petty, Mary, "House of the Seven Gables" (Box 31)
  - Writings & captions, Architectural Record, 3 folders (Box 31)
  - Reproductions from The New Yorker, 1926-1965; undated; 8 folders (Box 32)
  - Reproductions, 1956-1964 (Box 32)
  - Reproductions - newspages and magazine work, 1926-1927 (Box 32)
- Subject files
  - Alcohol, New Yorker, 23 Jan 1960 (Box 33)
  - Architecture, 7 folders (Box 33)
  - Architecture - water (Box 33)
  - Art pages (Box 33)
  - Cartoonists (Box 34)
  - Colour (Box 34)
  - Hardwoods (Box 34)
  - Human body (Box 34)
  - Investing (Box 34)
  - New Yorker cartoons, mixed artists and years, 7 folders (Box 34)
  - New Yorker cartoons, 4 folders (Box 35)
  - New Yorker covers
    - Addams, Charles (Box 35)
    - Allen, Laura J. (Box 35)
    - Anno, Peter (Box 35)
    - Barlow, P. (Box 35)
    - Birnbaum, A. (Box 35)
    - François, Andre (Box 35)
    - Getz (Box 35)
    - Hubbell, Albert (Box 35)
    - Karasz (Box 35)
    - Kovarsky (Box 35)
    - Kraus (Box 35)
    - C.E.M. (Box 35)
    - Mahood (Box 35)
    - Modell, F.B. (Box 35)
    - Price, Garrett (Box 35)
    - Saxon (Box 35)
    - Steig (Box 35)
    - Steinberg (Box 35)
  - [Physics] (Box 35)
  - Punch cartoons (Box 35)
  - Saturday Review cartoons (Box 35)
  - Thelwell (cartoonist) (Box 35)
  - War (Box 35)
  - Miscellaneous printed material, 2 folders (Box 35, 36)
  - Small oils and watercolors, field sketches? (Box 36)
  - Card files of cartoons used (Box 37, 38)
  - Maps, Coldstream and the Bedford plan, 2 untitled cartoon publications (Oversize 1)
  - Enough time, the pattern of the executive life, book dummy (Oversize 2)
  - New Yorker Dunn cartoons, 1930-1940; 1926-1955; 2 volumes (Oversize 3)